

Mehdi Momen Statistical and Quantitative Geneticist November 2018

CONTACT Information Department of Animal and Poultry Sciences Virginia Tech Blacksburg, USA (+1) (571) 299 0608 momenmehdi@vt.edu

RESEARCH INTERESTS I am a statistical and quantitative geneticist interested in applying statistical learning methods to multi-layer omic data. My research interests span a broad range of topics including animal breeding, plant breeding, and human quantitative genetics.

EDUCATION

Shahid Bahonar University Of Kerman (SBUK), Kerman, IRAN Ph.D. Animal Breeding and Genetics, April 2017

- Dissertation: "Predictive ability and sensitivity of Whole Genome Prediction (WGP) statistical Models for Genomic Selection in complex Traits with Additive, Dominance and Epistatic Genetic Architecture."
- Advisor: Ahmad Ayatollahi Mehrgardi & Ali Esmailizadeh

University of Wisconsin-Madison, Madison, Wisconsin, USA

Visiting Ph.D. Student. Animal Breeding and Genetics, October 2015 - Jun 2016

- Project: "Development and predictive assessment of whole-genome prediction machines in Genomic selection and Genome-wide association studies"
- Advisor: Daniel Gianola

Tehran University, Aboureihan Campus, Tehran, IRAN

M.S. Genetic and Animal Breeding, May 2010

- Dissertation: "Genetic Analysis of Reproductive and Growth traits In Purebred and Crossbred Lambs from three Iranian Sheep Breeds"
- Advisor: Nasser Emam-Jomea Kashan

Zabol University, Agricultural College, Sistan Province, IRAN

B.S. Animal Science, May 2007

• Advisor: Nasser Emam-Jomea Kashan

EMPLOYMENT

Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Virginia, USA

Post-doctoral Researcher in Statistical and Quantitative Genetics, November 2018 - Present

• Advisor: Gota Morota

Shahid Bahonar University of Kerman (SBUK), Kerman, Iran.

Researcher in Statistical Genetics and Genomics, November 2017 - November 2018

• Advisor: Ahmad Ayatollahi Mehrgardi & Ali Esmailizadeh

Editorial and Activities

Reviewed for Journals:

Journal of Livestock Science and Technologies (12 papers), Italian Journal of Animal Science (1 paper)

Publications

Papers Under Review:

1. Mahmoud Amiri Roudbar, Mohammad Reza Mohammadabadi, Ahmad Ayatollahi Mehrgardi, Rostam Abdollahi-Arpanahi, <u>Mehdi Momen</u>, Gota Morota, Fernando Brito Lopese, Daniel Gianola, Guilherme J. M. Rosa,; *Jointure of single nucleotide variants and whole-genome DNA methylation profiles for classification of rheumatoid arthritis cases from controls*(Scientific Reports).

Published Papers:

- 1. Y. Fazel., A. Esmailizadeh Koshkoieh, <u>Momen M.,</u>M.Assadi Foozi. 2018 Importance of genotype by environment interaction on genetic analysis of milk yield in Iranian Holstein cows using random regression model. *Animal Production Science*. (DOI:doi.org/10.1071/AN17714).
- Momen M., A. Ayatollahi Mehrgardi, M. Amiri Roudbar, A. Kranis, R. Mercuri Pinto, B.D. Valente, G. Morota, G.J.M. Rosa, D. Gianola. 2018. Including phenotypic causal networks in genome-wide association studies using mixed effects structural equation models, Frontiers in Genetics (DOI: 10.3389/fgene.2018.00455).
- 3. <u>Momen M.</u>, Gota Morota. 2018.; Quantifying genomic connectedness and prediction accuracy from additive and non-additive gene actions. Genetics Selection Evolution, (DOI:10.1186/s12711-018-0415-9).
- Momen M., A. Ayatollahi Mehrgardi, A. Sheikhy, A. Kranis, L. Tusell, Gota Morota, G.J.M. Rosa, D. Gianola. 2018. Predictive ability of genome-assisted prediction machines under various statistical genetic architectures. Scientific Reports (DOI: 10.1038/s41598-018-30089-2).
- Momen M., A. Ayatollahi Mehrgardi, A. Sheikhy, A. Esmailizadeh Koshkoieh, M.Assadi Foozi, A. Kranis, B.D. Valente, G.J.M. Rosa, D. Gianola. 2017. A genome-enabled predictive assessment of genetic correlations between traits in chickens. Genetics Selection Evolution (DOI 10.1186/s12711-017-0290-9).
- Momen M., A. Ayatollahi Mehrgardi., A. Sheikhy., A.K. Esmailizadeh., M. Assadi Foozi. 2016. Predictive Ability of Statistical Genomic Prediction Methods When Underlying Genetic Architecture of Trait Is Purely Additive. Iranian Journal of Applied Animal Science (IJAS), Volume 6 (Issue 1): 822-815, Volume 6 (Issue 4).

Momen M., N. Emam Jomea Kashan, S.D. Sharifi, M. Amiri Roudbar, A. Ayatolahi Mehrgardi. 2015. Fatty acid composition of fat-tail and visceral fat depots from Chaal and Zandi pure lambs and their crosses with Zel (Three Iranian breeds). Iranian Journal of Applied Animal Science (IJAS), Volume 6 (Issue 1).

Posters:

- Momen M., A. Ayatollahi Mehrgardi, F. Brito Lopez., G.J.M. Rosa, D. Gianola. 2016. Combining marker and pedigree information may enhance multiple-trait genome-enabled prediction. 5th International Conferenceon Quantitative Genetics Madison, Wisconsin, USA.
- Jabari, M., F. sharifi, <u>Momen M.</u>. 2012. Aplication of Fuzzy Linear Regression(FLR) in agricultural economic studies.2012.1thInternational conference on Econometrics, Methods and Applications, Azad university of sanandaj, Iran, on 25-27 august 2012.
- 3. <u>Momen M.</u>, N.E.J Kashan, H. Sanjari. 2011. Study of Gut morphological traits in pure and crossbreeds lambs of Zandi with Zel. The 1th national conference on new technologies in agriculture science. Zanjan University, Zanjan province, Iran.
- N.E.J Kashan., <u>Momen M.</u>, Kh.nasiri. 2011. Simulation experiments to detection of quantitative trait loci (QTL, s) in Animal Populations.2011. The 1th national conference on new technologies in agriculture science. Zanjan University, Zanjan province, Iran.
- 5. Sanjari, H., <u>Momen M.</u>, N.E.J Kashan. 2011. Evaluation of the number and homozygosity of sex allelesin honey beecolonies.2011. The 1thnational conference onrearing management of livestock in tropical region. Kerman University, Kerman province, Iran.
- 6. <u>Momen M.</u>, Kh. Nasiri.2011. Genetic algorithm simulations for detection of quantitative traits loci effects.2011.the 5th national conference on new ideas in agriculture. Khorasgan azad university unit, Esfahan province, Iran.
- 7. Vesi .A, <u>Momen M.</u>, .2011. Application of Fuzzy logic in economic improvement of animal production units.2011.the 5th national conference on new ideas in agriculture. Khorasgan azad university unit, Esfahan province, Iran.
- 8. <u>Momen M.</u>, N.E.J Kashan, S.D. sharifi.2010. Investigation of fatty acids profile on fat-tail and visceral fats of Zandi pure lambs and their crosses with Zel rams. The 4th national conference in animal science. Tehran University, karaj campus, Iran.
- Momen M., N.E.J Kashan, S.D. sharifi. 2010. Study of relationship between blood-biochemical traits with carcass traits in pure lambs of Chal and Zandi and their cross with Zel rams. The 4th national conference in animal science. Tehran University, karaj campus, Iran.
- 10. <u>Momen M.</u>, N.E.J Kashan, S.D.Sharifi.2009. Study of growth performance on crossbreed lambs of fat-tailed and tailed sheep breeds, proceeding of The British

Society of Animal Science Association conference, Queen's University, Belfast, April, UK

- 11. Mohseni, M., N.E.J Kashan, <u>Momen M.</u>, 2009. Study seasonal and liver/lung condemnation in sheep, cattle and buffalo in khoy abattoir in northwest, Iran, Proceeding of The British Society of Animal Science Association conference, Queen's University, Belfast, April, UK.
- 12. Mohseni H., N.E.J Kashan., <u>Momen M.</u>,2009. An abattoir survey of the incidence of liver fluke disease and Hydatidosis in sheep in Khoy abattoir, West Azarbyjan, Iran, Proceeding of the British Society of Animal Science Association conference, Queen's University, Belfast, April, UK.

Presentations

- 1. Gain obtained by enriching whole genome prediction machines using genotypic data and bioinformatics initiative tools, Department of Animal Sciences, University of Tehran. (March 6, 2018)
- The Bayesian controversy in genome-enable prediction in animal breeding, Department of Animal Sciences, Shahid Bahonar University of Kerman (SBUK). (May 10, 2017)

Teaching Graduate courses

• Biostatistics, Quantitative Genetics, and Genomics in Animal Breeding, Statistical Analysis of Large Genomic data, Advance Genetic Prediction, Department of Animal Science, Shahid Bahonar University of University of Kerman, Kerman, Iran (2017-2018).

Undegraduate courses

- Biostatistics and Statistical in Agricultural Research, Department of Animal Science, University of Kerman, Kerman, Iran (2012-2018).
- General Biochemistry, department of agriculture improvement, Payam Noor University, Darab city, Fars province, Iran (2012).
- The basic of plant and animal genetic, department of agriculture improvement, Payam Noor University, Darab city, Fars province, Iran (2011).
- The basic of biotechnology in agricultural sciences, department of agriculture improvement, Payam Noor University, Darab city, Fars province, Iran (2011).
- Biostatistics and Statistical Designs in Agricultural Research as a teacher assistant, Department of Animal Science, University of Tehran, Tehran, Iran (2008).

SKILLS

Statistical and Genetic Software: ASReml, Wombat, BLUPf90, Plink, GCTA, GenSel, MCMCglmm, QTL Cartographer, Grid QTL, GenAlEx, SNPEVG, GVCBLUP, MEGA, and POPGENE

Programming Language: R, SAS, SPSS, C++, and LATEX

Additional Training

Short courses

- Genomic Selection in Animal and plant breeding. 2016. Instructor: Prof. Mike Goddard. In the framework of Annual A.B chapman lecture, February 6-8, Madison, Wisconsin, USA
- Genomic Selection in the Era of Genome Sequencing. 2016. Instructor: Ben Hayes. In the framework of 5th International Conference on Quantitative Genetics, January 6-8, Madison, Wisconsin, USA.
- Statistical Genetics of Quantitative Traits and Complex Disease. 2016. Instructor: Matt Robinson. In the framework of 5th International Conference on Quantitative Genetics, January 8-10, Madison, Wisconsin, USA.
- Genomic selection methods and analysis of huge genomic data in animal breeding programs and genomics. 2013. Instructor: Rostam Abdolahi-Arpanahi. August 26, Shahid Bahonar University of Kerman, Faculty of Agriculture (SBUK), Kerman, IRAN.
- Programming and advance data analysis with R software. 2013. Instructor: Rostam Abdolahi-Arpanahi. August 27-28, Shahid Bahonar University of Kerman(SBUK), Faculty of Agriculture, Kerman, IRAN.

References

Prof. Gota Morota,

Assistant Professor, Theoretical Quantitative Genetics Department of Animal and Poultry Sciences Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University morota@vt.edu http://morotalab.org

Prof. Daniel Gianola,

Sewall Wright Professor of Animal Breeding and Genetics
Department of Animal Sciences
Department of Biostatistics and Medical Informatics
Department of Dairy Science
University of Wisconsin-Madison
440 Animal Science Building
1675 Observatory Dr. Madison, WI53706, USA
Tel:+1 (608)265-2054
Fax:+1 (608)-262-5157
gianoal@ansci.wisc.edu
http://www.ansci.wisc.edu/Facultypages/gianola.html
htts://www.biostat.wisc.edu/content/gianola-daniel
http://qbi.wisc.edu/gianola-daniel.htm

Prof. Guilherme J.M. Rosa

Professor in Quantitative Genetic and Genomics Department of Animal Sciences Department of Biostatistics and Medical Informatics University of Wisconsin-Madison 436 Animal Science Building 1675Observatory Dr. Madison, WI53706USA Phone:+1(608)265-8617

Fax: +1 (608) 263-9412

grosa@wisc.edu

http://www.ansci.wisc.edu/Facultypages/rosa.html